Guide to the Durham Chamber of Commerce Records, circa 1910-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Durham Chamber of Commerce records circa 1910-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Greater Durham Chamber of Commerce.
4.0 linear feet Extent: 150 Items
The Greater Durham Chamber of Commerce serves the needs of businesses, non-profits, and government agencies of all sizes by helping to create and sustain a healthy economic climate. The collection largely contains photographs of Durham businesses, homes, schools, places of worship, and individuals. It also includes two bound volumes of meeting minutes, by-laws, and correspondence which date from 1915-1923 as well as material sent to members, such as newsletters.
RL.00363
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Durham Chamber of Commerce Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1975 and 1983.
Historical Note
The Greater Durham Chamber of Commerce serves the needs of businesses, non-profits, and government agencies of all sizes by helping to create and sustain a healthy economic climate. It was established in 1906.
Collection Overview
Collection contains photographic prints of buildings and persons in Durham, taken during the early to mid-twentieth century. There are also two minute books, one dated 1915-1919 and the other, 1919-1923. The first includes minutes of the Women's Classification of the Chamber and discussion of offering money to the Board of Health in an attempt to stamp out the influenza epidemic. The second volume includes discussion of gratitude to James B. and Benjamin N. Duke for money given towards the building of Lincoln Hospital. There is also material the Chamber sent to members, including newsletters and updates on Chamber activities.
The photographs have been largely identified, except where noted. Most of the images are of Durham buildings. Several photographs include the photographers stamp, the most common of which was the Halladay Studio.
Subject Headings
Durham (N.C.)--History
Contents of Collection
- Photographs, circa 1910-1958, (3 boxes)
  The images have been largely identified, with some exceptions (noted). The images in boxes 2-3 are mounted and were once part of a bound album.
  - Buildings, Structures, and Aerial Views
    - Wright Refuge (2 copies), N. Roxboro Rd., circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John Sprunt Hill House, S. Duke St., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified House, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified Property with Various Structures (possibly a farm), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - McPherson Hospital, W. Main St., circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Durham County Jail, Broad St., circa late 1920s (later Tuberculosis Sanitarium) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Durham County Home (2 different images), N. Roxboro Rd., circa late 1920s-early 1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - King's Daughters Home, Buchanan Blvd., mid-1920s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Watts Hospital (aerial), Broad St., circa late 1920s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Durham Cotton Manufacturing Company, E. Pettigrew St., circa late 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Wright Machinery Company, Holloway St., circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Yarbrough Mills (interior), Holloway St., circa 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rendering of Unidentified Building, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Durham Traction Company (includes horses, motorized truck with 2 unidentified men), Vivian St., circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Waverly Ice Cream, Holland St., circa late 1920s-early 1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Carolina Theatre, Roney St., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Home Security Life Insurance Company, Main/Market Sts., circa late 1920s-early 1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Wonderland Theater (2 copies), E. Pettigrew St., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Street Scene with Unidentified Buildings, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - View of Unidentified Buildings along Corcoran St. (looking north from W. Peabody St.), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Piedmont Building, W. Main St., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cheek-Holton Manufacturing Company, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Virginia-Carolina Chemical Company (2 copies), Angier Ave., circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cary Lumber Company (2 copies), S. Buchanan Blvd., circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Liggett and Myers Chesterfield Building, W. Main St., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Back of Old Post Office, located at Main and Corcoran (looking east across Corcoran), with bags of mail piled up, circa late 1920s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Louise Knitting Mill/Griffin Hosiery Mill, N. Maple St., circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Golden Belt Manufacturing Company, Franklin St., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bassett-Brown House, N. Buchanan Blvd., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Leary/Coletta House, Cleveland St., circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Four Acres, W. Chapel Hill St., circa late 1920s-mid-1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Durham Athletic Park, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photo of "Design of Proposed Durham Country Club" (rendering of exterior), Atwood and Nash, Inc. Architects, Durham, NC, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photo of "Durham Country Club" (rendering of exterior), Milburn, Heister and Co. Architects, Washington, DC/Durham, NC, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Fire Station No. 3 (includes fire truck and 4 firemen), circa late 1920s-mid-1930s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Southern Conservatory of Music, Alston Ave., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Powe Apartments, N. Buchanan Blvd., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The People's Bank, S. Driver St., circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Merchants Bank, W. Main St., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - YMCA, E. Main St., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - YMCA, W. Trinity Ave., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Trust Building, W. Main St., circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Main Public Library (2 copies), E. Main St., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified Textile Mill Interior, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Textile Mill Interior, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Textile Mill Interior, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Textile Mill Interior (note milling machinery manufactured by Nordyke and Marmon Co. of Indianapolis, IN), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Construction Site, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Clerk's Desk [?] (probably from a textile company), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified Street with Christmas Decorations (lit up at night), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified Concrete Bridge over Railroad Tracks (includes a train car and an unidentified person bending over in the background; one unidentified woman is at the support base of bridge; one unidentified woman is standing higher than the support base, closer to the bridge, and is holding a ukelele), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Aerial view of tobacco warehouses and auction warehouses (note El Toro Baseball Park [Durham Athletic Park], circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Aerial view of downtown (features railroad, tobacco companies, churches), circa 1930s [?] (2 different views) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Aerial view overlooking E. Main St. (note Durham Public Service Company and Hotel Lochmoor), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Aerial view of Durham Cotton Manufacturing Company's complex (buildings/structures are numbered but the legend is not available), circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Panoramic view of downtown facing Hotel Lochmoor and the YMCA. Railroad tracks and watertowers are visible. circa 1920s (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of the American Tobacco Company, 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of American Tobacco Company (note residential houses), 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of Durham from the Washington Duke Hotel, looking west, 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of the Golden Belt Manufacturing Company, 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of Erwin Mills complex and mill houses, circa 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of the Erwin Mills complex, 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of Durham from the top of an unidentified building. Durham Public Service Company is visible on the right. 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic view of the Liggett and Myers plant, looking down Main St. where it intersects with Duke St., 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - People
    - Dr. Bartlett Durham, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified Durham Policeman (wearing a western bow tie and western-style hat w/ badge attached), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 5 Unidentified Men at Civic Event Honoring Merrill P. "Tootsie" Knight (includes framed award, one man is presumably Knight), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified Posed Group of 16 People (includes 2 women, group is in unidentified room), circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified Group of 19 Men Posed on the Sidewalk in Front of Pritchard and Bright Clothing Store, W. Main St., circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified Group of 22 Men Posed Inside an Unidentified Room (William A. Kirkland, Sr., has been identified as the 8th person from the left on the front row), circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Four Men at an Awards Ceremony, Identified on the Image as Biggs, Carlton (holding award), Baynes, and Chambers (holding award), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified People on Street Corner, near 217 Chapel Hill St. (Some individuals are waiting to board a bus with stops in Raleigh-Durham-Greensboro. The driver is standing on top of the bus, loading up passenger luggage.), circa mid-late 1920s-early 1930s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Children and Adults at Durham's First Playground (2 different images), S. Duke St., circa 1910-1919 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Panoramic, Dinner Honoring Eddie Rickenbacker, undated. Photo shows 15 unidentified people sitting at a dais. (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic, Unidentified large group of people (men and women) posed by what appears to be a farmhouse. Some are dressed in regular clothes while others are in uniform. 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Panoramic, Attendees (men and women) to the Monarch Convention, 1926. (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Parade, early 1940s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mounted Photographs, circa 1950s
    - Side One: Aerial View of Downtown Overlooking Chapel Hill St., railroad tracks, and Main St.; Side Two: Blank (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Side One: Brogden Junion High School; Side Two: East Durham Junior High School (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Side One: Club Blvd. Elementary School; Side Two: Watts St. Elementary School (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Side One: Southside Grammar School; Side Two: E. K. Powe School (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Side One: Southern High School; Side Two: Lowes Grove School (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Side One: Northern High School; Side Two: Blank (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Side One: Durham Academy (S. Duke St.), Unidentified House; Side Two: Twaddell School, Unidentified House (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Side One: Duke Chapel; Side Two: Duke University Union Building and Duke Chapel (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Side One: Aerial View of East Campus, Duke University; Side Two: Sarah P. Duke Memorial Gardens (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Side One: Summer House, Sarah P. Duke Memorial Gardens; Side Two: Fountain, Sarah P. Duke Memorial Gardens (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Side One: First Baptist Church; Side Two: Temple Baptist Church (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Side One: First Presbyterian Church (Main St.); Side Two: Trinity Methodist Church (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Side One: Immaculate Conception Church (Chapel Hill St.); Side Two: Beth-El Synagogue (Watts St.) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Side One: Duke Memorial Methodist Church; Side Two: Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Side One: St. Philip's Episcopal Church (Main St.); Side Two: St. Andrews Episcopal Church (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Mounted Photographs, circa 1950s
    - Side One: Grace Baptist Church; Side Two: Calvary Methodist Church (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Side One: St. Paul's Lutheran Church; Side Two: Blank (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Side One: Watts St. Baptist Church; Side Two: St. Barbara Greek Orthodox Church (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Side One: Epworth Methodist Church; Side Two: Holloway St. Christian Church (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Side One: St. John Methodist Church [later Chapel of the Methodist Retirement Home]; Side Two: Braggtown Baptist Church (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Side One: Veteran's Administration Hospital; Side Two: Methodist Retirement Home (Erwin Rd.) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Side One: YWCA (Chapel Hill St.); Side Two: Blank (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Side One: U. S. Army Reserve; Side Two: National Guard Armory (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Side One: U. S. Naval and Marine Corps Reserve Training Center; Side Two: Durham County Stadium (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Side One: Hope Valley Country Club; Side Two: Hillandale Golf Course (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Side One: Hillandale Golf Course Club House [original]; Side Two: Blank except for description of side one (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Side One: GTE Building (Roxboro Rd.); Side Two: Crum and Forster Group Building (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Side One: Aerial View of Tobacco Warehouses; Side Two: Aerial View of Tobacco Warehouses (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Side One: Aerial View of Erwin Mills; Side Two: Blank (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Side One: Forest Hills Shopping Center; Side Two: Blank (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Business Records, 1915-1923, (2 boxes)
  - Bound Volume: By-laws, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence to Board Members, 1915-1919 (includes index) (Box 4)
  - Bound Volume: Meeting Minutes, Resolutions, Correspondence to Board Members, 1919-1923 (includes index) (Box 5)
- Membership Material, 1971-1981, (2 folders)
  - "Action" Newsletter, 1972 Oct., 1979-1981 (incomplete) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Correspondence to Members, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)